Alice Notley Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Alice Notley Papers.
1970-1992
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Notley, Alice.
2 linear feet.
Alice Notley, born in 1945, is an American poet, author, and editor.
MSS19980222
Biography
Alice Notley, born in Bisbee, Arizona, in 1945, is a recognized American poet, author, and editor. Among the numerous collections of verse that she has published are Incidentals in the Day World (Angel Hair Books, 1973), When I Was Alive, (Vehicle Edition, 1980), Waltzing Matilda, (Kulchur Foundation, 1981), Margaret and Dusty (Coffee House Press, 1985), and How Spring Comes (Toothpaste Press, 1981). In addition to her poetry, Notley wrote a short autobiography entitled Tell Me Again (Am Here Books, 1982). Editor of the Scarlet Magazine, Notley was married to Ted Berrigan (1934-1983), who is also a poet.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and collages. Correspondents include Robert Creeley, Anselm Hollo, Sal Salasin, Ron Padgett and Kate Ferrell whose work was published in the Scarlet Magazine. Drafts of the first five issues of the journal are included in the collection. Two photographs (Charles Olson in his casket and Olson's typewriter) are located in Series I.
One of the more significant documents in the collection is Notley's long, personal narrative poem “The Descent of Alette” (1992) which was published in The Scarlet Cabinet.
Notley created many elaborate collages, which are included in the collection, although undated.
This collection was originally included in the Ted Berrigan Papers. The collections were separated in 1997 as a result of later additions of Notley materials.
Arrangement
Series I: Business Papers ( 1970-1992 ) consists of correspondence, notecards, draft issues of Scarlet nos. 1-5, and related poetry materials.
Series II: Writings ( 1992 ) consists of the narrative poem “The Descent of Alette”.
Series III: Collages ( undated ) consists of undated collages and cartoons.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Alice Smith Haynes. ed. Donald J. Greiner, “Ted Berrigan,” in American Poets since World War II, Part I, Dictionary of Literary Biography, vol. 5 (Detroit: Gale Research, 1980 ).
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Poets, American--20th century.; American poetry--20th century.; Editors and publishers--United States.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Draft Publications.; Artwork.; Photographs.
Occupations:
Poet.; Author.; Editor.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Unknown provenance. Possible purchase.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Business Papers, 1970-1992
  - Notley Correspondence, 1973-1991 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Notley Postcards, 1977-1992 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Scarlet #1, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Scarlet #2, 1990 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Scarlet #3, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Scarlet #4, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Scarlet #5, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Related poetry materials, 1970-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
- Series II: Writings, 1992
  - “The Descent of Alette”, 1992 (Box 2:, Folder 9)
- Series III: Collages, undated
  - Collages, undated (Box 2:, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Collage, undated (Box 3:, Folder 11)
  - Cartoons by Joe Brainard, Ron Padgett and Ted Berrigan, undated (Box 3)